<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
  <records>
    <record>
      <ref-type name="Journal Article"></ref-type>
      <contributors>
        <authors>
          <author>
            Alcaraz, Kassandra I.
          </author>
          <author>
            Wiedt, Tracy L.
          </author>
          <author>
            Daniels, Elvan C.
          </author>
          <author>
            Yabroff, K. Robin
          </author>
          <author>
            Guerra, Carmen E.
          </author>
          <author>
            Wender, Richard C.
          </author>
        </authors>
        <secondary-authors>
        </secondary-authors>
      </contributors>
      <titles>
        <title>Understanding and addressing social determinants to advance cancer health equity in the United States: A blueprint for practice, research, and policy</title>
      </titles>
      <dates>
        <year>2020</year>
          <pub-dates>
            <date>1</date>
          </pub-dates>
      </dates>
      <volume>70</volume>
      <pages>31-46</pages>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <electronic-resource-num>10.3322&#x2F;caac.21586</electronic-resource-num>
      <abstract>Although cancer mortality rates declined in the United States in recent decades, some populations experienced little benefit from advances in cancer prevention, early detection, treatment, and survivorship care. In fact, some cancer disparities between populations of low and high socioeconomic status widened during this period. Many potentially preventable cancer deaths continue to occur, and disadvantaged populations bear a disproportionate burden. Reducing the burden of cancer and eliminating cancer‐related disparities will require more focused and coordinated action across multiple sectors and in partnership with communities. This article, part of the American Cancer Society&#39;s Cancer Control Blueprint series, introduces a framework for understanding and addressing social determinants to advance cancer health equity and presents actionable recommendations for practice, research, and policy. The article aims to accelerate progress toward eliminating disparities in cancer and achieving health equity.</abstract>
      <periodical><full-title>CA: A Cancer Journal for Clinicians</full-title></periodical>
      <keywords>
      </keywords>
      <urls>
        <related-urls>
        </related-urls>
      </urls>
    </record>
    <record>
      <ref-type name="Journal Article"></ref-type>
      <contributors>
        <authors>
          <author>
            Brakefield, Whitney S.
          </author>
          <author>
            Olusanya, Olufunto A.
          </author>
          <author>
            White, Brianna
          </author>
          <author>
            Shaban-Nejad, Arash
          </author>
        </authors>
        <secondary-authors>
        </secondary-authors>
      </contributors>
      <titles>
        <title>Social Determinants and Indicators of COVID-19 Among Marginalized Communities: A Scientific Review and Call to Action for Pandemic Response and Recovery</title>
      </titles>
      <dates>
        <year>2023</year>
          <pub-dates>
            <date>5</date>
          </pub-dates>
      </dates>
      <volume>17</volume>
      <pages>e193</pages>
      <electronic-resource-num>10.1017&#x2F;dmp.2022.104</electronic-resource-num>
      <abstract>Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) has placed massive socio-psychological, health, and economic burdens including deaths on countless lives; however, it has disproportionally impacted certain populations. Co-occurring Social Determinants of Health (SDoH) disparities and other underlying determinants have exacerbated the COVID-19 pandemic. This literature review sought to (1) examine literature focused on SDoH and COVID-19 outcomes ie, infectivity, hospitalization, and death rates among marginalized communities; and (2) identify SDoH disparities associated with COVID-19 outcomes. We searched electronic databases for studies published from October 2019 to October 2021. Studies that were selected were those intersecting SDoH indicators and COVID-19 outcomes and were conducted in the United States. Our review underscored the disproportionate vulnerabilities and adverse outcomes from COVID-19 that have impacted racial&#x2F;ethnic minority communities and other disadvantaged groups (ie, senior citizens, and displaced&#x2F;homeless individuals). COVID-19 outcomes were associated with SDoH indicators, ie, race&#x2F;ethnicity, poverty, median income level, housing density, housing insecurity, health-care access, occupation, transportation&#x2F;commuting patterns, education, air quality, food insecurity, old age, etc. Our review concluded with recommendations and a call to action to integrate SDoH indicators along with relevant health data when implementing intelligent solutions and intervention strategies to pandemic response&#x2F;recovery among vulnerable populations.</abstract>
      <periodical><full-title>Disaster Medicine and Public Health Preparedness</full-title></periodical>
      <keywords>
      </keywords>
      <urls>
        <related-urls>
        </related-urls>
      </urls>
    </record>
    <record>
      <ref-type name="Journal Article"></ref-type>
      <contributors>
        <authors>
          <author>
            Cerin, Ester
          </author>
          <author>
            Leslie, Eva
          </author>
          <author>
            Owen, Neville
          </author>
        </authors>
        <secondary-authors>
        </secondary-authors>
      </contributors>
      <titles>
        <title>Explaining socio-economic status differences in walking for transport: An ecological analysis of individual, social and environmental factors</title>
      </titles>
      <dates>
        <year>2009</year>
          <pub-dates>
            <date>3</date>
          </pub-dates>
      </dates>
      <volume>68</volume>
      <pages>1013-1020</pages>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <electronic-resource-num>10.1016&#x2F;j.socscimed.2009.01.008</electronic-resource-num>
      <abstract>The identification of potential mechanisms of influence (mediators) of socio-economic status (SES) on walking for transport is important, because the likely opposing forces of influence may obscure pathways for intervention across different SES groups. This study examined individual, and perceived social and physical environmental mediators of the relations of individual- and area-level SES with walking for transport. Two mailed surveys, six months apart, collected data on transport-related walking and its hypothesized individual, social and environmental correlates. The sample consisted of 2194 English-speaking adults (aged 20–65) living in 154 Census Collection Districts (CCDs) of Adelaide, Australia. Individual-level SES was assessed using data on self-reported educational attainment, household income, and household size. Area-level SES was assessed using census data on median household income and household size for each selected CCD. Bootstrap generalized linear models examined associations between SES, potential mediators, and total weekly minutes and frequency of walking for transport. The product-of-coefficient test was used to assess mediating effects. Individual, social–environmental, and physical environmental factors significantly contributed to the explanation of the relations between SES and transport-related walking frequency. Educational attainment and area- and individual-level income played independent roles in explaining frequency of walking for transport, through opposing common and distinct pathways. While engagement in leisure-time physical activity was the most influential mediator of the association between educational attainment and frequency of walking for transport, the number of motorized vehicles and perceived levels of environmental aesthetics and greenery were the strongest mediators of the relations of frequency of transport-related walking with individual- and area-level income, respectively. Environmental interventions aimed at increasing residential density, reducing physical barriers to walking and traffic load, developing social-support networks, and creating greener and more aesthetically pleasing environments in more-disadvantaged areas may help to reduce SES inequalities in participation in physical activity, by facilitating walking for transport.</abstract>
      <periodical><full-title>Social Science &amp; Medicine</full-title></periodical>
      <keywords>
      </keywords>
      <urls>
        <related-urls>
        </related-urls>
      </urls>
    </record>
    <record>
      <ref-type name="Journal Article"></ref-type>
      <contributors>
        <authors>
          <author>
            Chen, Katherine L.
          </author>
          <author>
            Brozen, Madeline
          </author>
          <author>
            Rollman, Jeffrey E.
          </author>
          <author>
            Ward, Tayler
          </author>
          <author>
            Norris, Keith C.
          </author>
          <author>
            Gregory, Kimberly D.
          </author>
          <author>
            Zimmerman, Frederick J.
          </author>
        </authors>
        <secondary-authors>
        </secondary-authors>
      </contributors>
      <titles>
        <title>How is the COVID-19 pandemic shaping transportation access to health care?</title>
      </titles>
      <dates>
        <year>2021</year>
          <pub-dates>
            <date>6</date>
          </pub-dates>
      </dates>
      <volume>10</volume>
      <pages>100338</pages>
      <electronic-resource-num>10.1016&#x2F;j.trip.2021.100338</electronic-resource-num>
      <abstract>The Coronavirus disease 19 (COVID-19) pandemic has disrupted both transportation and health systems. While about 40% of Americans have delayed seeking medical care during the pandemic, it remains unclear to what extent transportation is contributing to missed care. To understand the relationship between transportation and unmet health care needs during the pandemic, this paper synthesizes existing knowledge on transportation patterns and barriers across five types of health care needs. While the literature is limited by the absence of detailed data for trips to health care, key themes emerged across populations and settings. We find that some patients, many of whom already experience transportation disadvantage, likely need extra support during the pandemic to overcome new travel barriers related to changes in public transit or the inability to rely on others for rides. Telemedicine is working as a partial substitute for some visits but cannot fulfill all health care needs, especially for vulnerable groups. Structural inequality during the pandemic has likely compounded health care access barriers for low-income individuals and people of color, who face not only disproportionate health risks, but also greater difficulty in transportation access and heightened economic hardship due to COVID-19. Partnerships between health and transportation systems hold promise for jointly addressing disparities in health- and transportation-related challenges but are largely limited to Medicaid-enrolled patients. Our findings suggest that transportation and health care providers should look for additional strategies to ensure that transportation access is not a reason for delayed medical care during and after the COVID-19 pandemic.</abstract>
      <periodical><full-title>Transportation Research Interdisciplinary Perspectives</full-title></periodical>
      <keywords>
      </keywords>
      <urls>
        <related-urls>
        </related-urls>
      </urls>
    </record>
    <record>
      <ref-type name="Journal Article"></ref-type>
      <contributors>
        <authors>
          <author>
            Clark, Lara P.
          </author>
          <author>
            Millet, Dylan B.
          </author>
          <author>
            Marshall, Julian D.
          </author>
        </authors>
        <secondary-authors>
        </secondary-authors>
      </contributors>
      <titles>
        <title>Changes in Transportation-Related Air Pollution Exposures by Race-Ethnicity and Socioeconomic Status: Outdoor Nitrogen Dioxide in the United States in 2000 and 2010</title>
      </titles>
      <dates>
        <year>2017</year>
          <pub-dates>
            <date>9</date>
          </pub-dates>
      </dates>
      <volume>125</volume>
      <issue>9</issue>
      <electronic-resource-num>10.1289&#x2F;EHP959</electronic-resource-num>
      <abstract>Background:
Disparities in exposure to air pollution by race-ethnicity and by socioeconomic status have been documented in the United States, but the impacts of declining transportation-related air pollutant emissions on disparities in exposure have not been studied in detail.
Objective:
This study was designed to estimate changes over time (2000 to 2010) in disparities in exposure to outdoor concentrations of a transportation-related air pollutant, nitrogen dioxide (NO2), in the United States.
Methods:
We combined annual average NO2 concentration estimates from a temporal land use regression model with Census demographic data to estimate outdoor exposures by race-ethnicity, socioeconomic characteristics (income, age, education), and by location (region, state, county, urban area) for the contiguous United States in 2000 and 2010.
Results:
Estimated annual average NO2 concentrations decreased from 2000 to 2010 for all of the race-ethnicity and socioeconomic status groups, including a decrease from 17.6 ppb to 10.7 ppb (−6.9 ppb) in nonwhite [non-(white alone, non-Hispanic)] populations, and 12.6 ppb to 7.8 ppb (−4.7 ppb) in white (white alone, non-Hispanic) populations. In 2000 and 2010, disparities in NO2 concentrations were larger by race-ethnicity than by income. Although the national nonwhite–white mean NO2 concentration disparity decreased from a difference of 5.0 ppb in 2000 to 2.9 ppb in 2010, estimated mean NO2 concentrations remained 37% higher for nonwhites than whites in 2010 (40% higher in 2000), and nonwhites were 2.5 times more likely than whites to live in a block group with an average NO2 concentration above the WHO annual guideline in 2010 (3.0 times more likely in 2000).
Conclusions:
Findings suggest that absolute NO2 exposure disparities by race-ethnicity decreased from 2000 to 2010, but relative NO2 exposure disparities persisted, with higher NO2 concentrations for nonwhites than whites in 2010.</abstract>
      <periodical><full-title>Environmental Health Perspectives</full-title></periodical>
      <keywords>
      </keywords>
      <urls>
        <related-urls>
        </related-urls>
      </urls>
    </record>
    <record>
      <ref-type name="Journal Article"></ref-type>
      <contributors>
        <authors>
          <author>
            Des Rosiers, François
          </author>
          <author>
            Thériault, Marius
          </author>
          <author>
            Biba, Gjin
          </author>
          <author>
            Vandersmissen, Marie-Hélène
          </author>
        </authors>
        <secondary-authors>
        </secondary-authors>
      </contributors>
      <titles>
        <title>Greenhouse gas emissions and urban form: Linking households’ socio-economic status with housing and transportation choices</title>
      </titles>
      <dates>
        <year>2017</year>
          <pub-dates>
            <date>9</date>
          </pub-dates>
      </dates>
      <volume>44</volume>
      <pages>964-985</pages>
      <issue>5</issue>
      <electronic-resource-num>10.1177&#x2F;0265813516656862</electronic-resource-num>
      <abstract>The main purpose of this research is to provide new insights for reducing greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions linked to transportation, furthering our knowledge on linkages between urban form and economic constraints, travel behaviour, and ability-to-pay of households based on residential choices and property ownership statuses. With Quebec City (Canada) as a case study, it combines an origin-destination (OD) survey, population census data and land use records for 2006 and rests on a series of structural equations models developed at the grid cell level (3,892 cells), which allows for testing for both direct and indirect effects of urban form, accessibility and socio-economic attributes on GHG emissions, households’ transportation and housing financial burdens and motorization rate. As expected, findings suggest that GHG emissions increase with higher incomes (and education), but mainly for homeowners. Tenants displaying a high expenditure-to-income ratio for housing tend to stay close to the city centre (and jobs), thereby minimizing their overall expenditures for transportation while lowering GHG emissions. Potential accessibility by car promotes urban sprawl, thereby contributing to increased GHG emissions. In contrast, increasing residential density and land use mix while providing a better walking access to jobs and local shops tends to favour active transportation, leading to a significant reduction in GHG emissions.</abstract>
      <periodical><full-title>Environment and Planning B: Urban Analytics and City Science</full-title></periodical>
      <keywords>
      </keywords>
      <urls>
        <related-urls>
        </related-urls>
      </urls>
    </record>
    <record>
      <ref-type name="Journal Article"></ref-type>
      <contributors>
        <authors>
          <author>
            Graboyes, Evan M
          </author>
          <author>
            Chaiyachati, Krisda H
          </author>
          <author>
            Sisto Gall, Jennifer
          </author>
          <author>
            Johnson, Wenora
          </author>
          <author>
            Krishnan, Jerry A
          </author>
          <author>
            McManus, Sapna S
          </author>
          <author>
            Thompson, Letitia
          </author>
          <author>
            Shulman, Lawrence N
          </author>
          <author>
            Yabroff, K Robin
          </author>
        </authors>
        <secondary-authors>
        </secondary-authors>
      </contributors>
      <titles>
        <title>Addressing Transportation Insecurity Among Patients With Cancer</title>
      </titles>
      <dates>
        <year>2022</year>
          <pub-dates>
            <date>12</date>
          </pub-dates>
      </dates>
      <volume>114</volume>
      <pages>1593-1600</pages>
      <issue>12</issue>
      <electronic-resource-num>10.1093&#x2F;jnci&#x2F;djac134</electronic-resource-num>
      <abstract>Health-care–related transportation insecurity is common in the United States. Patients with cancer are especially vulnerable because cancer care is episodic in nature, occurs over a prolonged period, is marked by frequent clinical encounters, requires intense treatments, and results in substantial financial hardship. As a result of transportation insecurity, patients with cancer may forego, miss, delay, alter, and&#x2F;or prematurely terminate necessary care. Limited data suggest that these alterations in care have the potential to increase the rates of cancer recurrence and mortality and exacerbate disparities in cancer incidence, severity, and outcomes. Transportation insecurity also negatively impacts at the informal caregiver, provider, health system, and societal levels. Recognizing that transportation is a critical determinant of outcomes for patients with cancer, there are ongoing efforts to develop evidence-based protocols to identify at-risk patients and address transportation insecurity at federal policy, health system, not-for-profit, and industry levels. In 2021, the National Cancer Policy Forum of the National Academies of Science, Engineering, and Medicine sponsored a series of webinars addressing key social determinants of health including food, housing, and transportation among patients with cancer. This commentary summarizes the formal presentations and discussions related to transportation insecurity and will 1) discuss the heterogeneous nature of transportation insecurity among patients with cancer; 2) characterize its prevalence along the cancer continuum; 3) examine its multilevel consequences; 4) discuss measurement and screening tools; 5) highlight ongoing efforts to address transportation insecurity; 6) suggest policy levers; and 7) outline a research agenda to address critical knowledge gaps.</abstract>
      <periodical><full-title>JNCI: Journal of the National Cancer Institute</full-title></periodical>
      <keywords>
      </keywords>
      <urls>
        <related-urls>
        </related-urls>
      </urls>
    </record>
    <record>
      <ref-type name="Journal Article"></ref-type>
      <contributors>
        <authors>
          <author>
            Hansmann, Kellia J.
          </author>
          <author>
            Grabow, Maggie
          </author>
          <author>
            McAndrews, Carolyn
          </author>
        </authors>
        <secondary-authors>
        </secondary-authors>
      </contributors>
      <titles>
        <title>Health equity and active transportation: A scoping review of active transportation interventions and their impacts on health equity</title>
      </titles>
      <dates>
        <year>2022</year>
          <pub-dates>
            <date>6</date>
          </pub-dates>
      </dates>
      <volume>25</volume>
      <pages>101346</pages>
      <electronic-resource-num>10.1016&#x2F;j.jth.2022.101346</electronic-resource-num>
      <abstract>Background
Changes to the transportation system that promote active transportation – walking, cycling, public transit – can promote important population health gains. However, these potential benefits may not impact everyone equally. We do not know how much they may address, or conversely widen, existing racial and socioeconomic health disparities. This study aims to review existing research that investigates the distribution of health impacts of active transportation interventions across indicators of race, ethnicity, or socioeconomic status.
Methods
We conducted a scoping review of peer-reviewed literature and other significant research to identify studies using a longitudinal design to evaluate the health outcomes of an active transportation intervention, and to compare differences between groups based on race, ethnicity, or socioeconomic status. We searched PubMed, Scopus, Web of Science, and Transport Research International Documentation between January 1, 2000 and October 21, 2020.
Results
Our search resulted in 7226 records that we screened for keyword relevance by title. We identified 3246 abstracts to review further but ultimately found only 10 studies meeting all our inclusion criteria. These 10 studies evaluated behavior change programs, pedestrian and cycling infrastructure improvements, and increased transit infrastructure or access. Eight of these studies found that the intervention had a positive impact on health outcomes overall. When compared across indicators of participant race, ethnicity, or socioeconomic status, nine found either no significant difference or a favorable impact of the intervention on the health outcome for disadvantaged groups studied.
Conclusion
A significant gap in the literature persists, representing missed opportunities to further our understanding of how health inequities might be mitigated or addressed through changes in active transportation infrastructure, promotional campaigns, and policies. We call for researchers to include equity in the development of conceptual models, interventions, study design, and data analysis.</abstract>
      <periodical><full-title>Journal of Transport &amp; Health</full-title></periodical>
      <keywords>
      </keywords>
      <urls>
        <related-urls>
        </related-urls>
      </urls>
    </record>
    <record>
      <ref-type name="Journal Article"></ref-type>
      <contributors>
        <authors>
          <author>
            Lathrop, Breanna
          </author>
        </authors>
        <secondary-authors>
        </secondary-authors>
      </contributors>
      <titles>
        <title>Moving Toward Health Equity by Addressing Social Determinants of Health</title>
      </titles>
      <dates>
        <year>2020</year>
          <pub-dates>
            <date>2</date>
          </pub-dates>
      </dates>
      <volume>24</volume>
      <pages>36-44</pages>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <electronic-resource-num>10.1016&#x2F;j.nwh.2019.11.003</electronic-resource-num>
      <abstract>Social determinants of health—the conditions in which people are born, grow, work, live, and age that affect health and quality of life—are strongly associated with disparities in health status and life expectancy. Nurses require a comprehensive understanding of social determinants and their associations with health outcomes to provide patient-centered care. Nurses can be leaders and change agents in advancing health equity by screening for social determinants that affect women and by engaging in cross-sector collaboration to build partnerships outside the health care system to address complex social needs. Nurses can also use their experience and knowledge to advocate for system-level change, which is required to address the upstream factors influencing the health of women.</abstract>
      <periodical><full-title>Nursing for Women&#39;s Health</full-title></periodical>
      <keywords>
      </keywords>
      <urls>
        <related-urls>
        </related-urls>
      </urls>
    </record>
    <record>
      <ref-type name="Journal Article"></ref-type>
      <contributors>
        <authors>
          <author>
            Lee, Jinhyung
          </author>
          <author>
            Kim, Junghwan
          </author>
        </authors>
        <secondary-authors>
        </secondary-authors>
      </contributors>
      <titles>
        <title>Social equity analysis of public transit accessibility to healthcare might be erroneous when travel time uncertainty impacts are overlooked</title>
      </titles>
      <dates>
        <year>2023</year>
          <pub-dates>
            <date>7</date>
          </pub-dates>
      </dates>
      <volume>32</volume>
      <pages>100588</pages>
      <electronic-resource-num>10.1016&#x2F;j.tbs.2023.100588</electronic-resource-num>
      <abstract>Previous studies evaluating the social equity of transit-based accessibility to healthcare have failed to consider travel time uncertainty by assuming that transit always operates exactly as scheduled. Their analyses, therefore, tended to ignore travellers’ efforts to avoid being late to their healthcare appointments. These conventional approaches might overestimate accessibility and lead to inaccurate evaluations of social equity. This study aims to investigate how overlooking travellers’ risk-management efforts under travel time uncertainty might result in flawed assessments of equity in transit-based accessibility to healthcare facilities. Specifically, we compare the traditional accessibility approach to the robust space–time accessibility (RSTA) method, which considers travellers’ risk-management strategies (e.g., leaving early, choosing routes based not only on travel time but also travel time variability) depending on whether they are risk-neutral or risk-averse under travel time uncertainty. The RSTA model provides a more conservative, realistic, and user-centred view of transit-based accessibility. To demonstrate this, we conducted an empirical study of Columbus, Ohio, USA, using real-time transit big data. Our results show that traditional measures of accessibility that do not consider the impact of travel time uncertainty cannot accurately capture the social and racial inequity in healthcare accessibility via transit. However, the RSTA method reveals significant inequity in transit-based healthcare accessibility among residents in terms of their socio-economic and demographic status. Moreover, the conventional accessibility method evaluates the new bus rapid transit (BRT) service as promoting the accessibility of disadvantaged people, which the robust accessibility method revealed is not true.</abstract>
      <periodical><full-title>Travel Behaviour and Society</full-title></periodical>
      <keywords>
      </keywords>
      <urls>
        <related-urls>
        </related-urls>
      </urls>
    </record>
    <record>
      <ref-type name="Journal Article"></ref-type>
      <contributors>
        <authors>
          <author>
            Lhamsuren, Khandsuren
          </author>
          <author>
            Choijiljav, Tserendolgor
          </author>
          <author>
            Budbazar, Enkhtuya
          </author>
          <author>
            Vanchinkhuu, Surenchimeg
          </author>
          <author>
            Blanc, Diana Chang
          </author>
          <author>
            Grundy, John
          </author>
        </authors>
        <secondary-authors>
        </secondary-authors>
      </contributors>
      <titles>
        <title>Taking action on the social determinants of health: improving health access for the urban poor in Mongolia</title>
      </titles>
      <dates>
        <year>2012</year>
          <pub-dates>
            <date>12</date>
          </pub-dates>
      </dates>
      <volume>11</volume>
      <pages>15</pages>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <electronic-resource-num>10.1186&#x2F;1475-9276-11-15</electronic-resource-num>
      <abstract>Introduction
In recent years, the country of Mongolia (population 2.8 million) has experienced rapid social changes associated with economic growth, persisting socio-economic inequities and internal migration. In order to improve health access for the urban poor, the Ministry of Health developed a &quot;Reaching Every District&quot; strategy (RED strategy) to deliver an integrated package of key health and social services. The aim of this article is to present findings of an assessment of the implementation of the RED strategy, and, on the basis of this assessment, articulate lessons learned for equitable urban health planning.
Methods
Principal methods for data collection and analysis included literature review, barrier analysis of health access and in-depth interviews and group discussions with health managers and providers.
Findings
The main barriers to health access for the urban poor relate to interacting effects of poverty, unhealthy daily living environments, social vulnerability and isolation. Implementation of the RED strategy has resulted in increased health access for the urban poor, as demonstrated by health staff having reached new clients with immunization, family planning and ante-natal care services, and increased civil registrations which enable social service provision. Organizational effects have included improved partnerships for health and increased motivation of the health workforce. Important lessons learned from the early implementation of the RED strategy include the need to form strong partnerships among stakeholders at each level of the health system and in the community, as well as the need to develop a specific financing strategy to address the needs of the very poor. The diverse social context for health in an urban poor setting calls for a decentralized planning and partnership strategy, but with central level commitment towards policy guidance and financing of pro-poor urban health strategies.
Conclusions
Lessons from Mongolia mirror other international studies which point to the need to measure and take action on the social determinants of health at the local area level in order to adequately reduce persistent inequities in health care access for the urban poor.</abstract>
      <periodical><full-title>International Journal for Equity in Health</full-title></periodical>
      <keywords>
      </keywords>
      <urls>
        <related-urls>
        </related-urls>
      </urls>
    </record>
    <record>
      <ref-type name="Journal Article"></ref-type>
      <contributors>
        <authors>
          <author>
            Ma, Tracey
          </author>
          <author>
            Ivers, Rebecca
          </author>
          <author>
            Solar, John
          </author>
          <author>
            Simon, Aaron
          </author>
          <author>
            Leeuw, Evelyne de
          </author>
          <author>
            Clapham, Kathleen
          </author>
        </authors>
        <secondary-authors>
        </secondary-authors>
      </contributors>
      <titles>
        <title>Experiences of Older Aboriginal People in Navigating Transport Systems in an Urban Setting: An Indigenous Perspective on Transport Access, a Social Determinant of Health</title>
      </titles>
      <dates>
        <year>2022</year>
          <pub-dates>
            <date>10</date>
          </pub-dates>
      </dates>
      <volume>19</volume>
      <issue>21</issue>
      <abstract>Background: In Australia, Aboriginal people are underserved by the transport system and are less able to easily get to places they need to go than others. This is a part of a larger pattern of exclusion and inequity for Aboriginal people which affects their health, wellbeing, and social participation. Guided by a decolonising framework, this research explored how older Aboriginal people, whose pivotal roles in their families and communities require their mobility, experience the transportation system, providing an Indigenous-centred view of the accessibility of transportation options in society. Methods: Interviews drawing from the yarning technique were conducted with ten older Aboriginal people living in Greater Western Sydney and analysed qualitatively. Results: In addition to the cognitive labour required to decipher the rules of the transport system and organise commitments to match the scheduling of transport services, older Aboriginal people in this study experienced stigmatising attitudes and condescending treatment from service professionals and the public when traveling. Conclusions: This study suggests three potential ways that the current trajectory that underserves older Aboriginal people could be disrupted, relating to service design, the diversity and inclusion agenda, and the social determinants of Indigenous health.</abstract>
      <periodical><full-title>International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health</full-title></periodical>
      <keywords>
      </keywords>
      <urls>
        <related-urls>
        </related-urls>
      </urls>
    </record>
    <record>
      <ref-type name="Journal Article"></ref-type>
      <contributors>
        <authors>
          <author>
            McAndrews, Carolyn
          </author>
          <author>
            Rosenlieb, Evan G.
          </author>
          <author>
            Troy, Austin
          </author>
          <author>
            Marshall, Wesley E.
          </author>
        </authors>
        <secondary-authors>
        </secondary-authors>
      </contributors>
      <titles>
        <title>Mountain-Plains Consortium</title>
      </titles>
      <dates>
        <year>2017</year>
          <pub-dates>
            <date>6</date>
          </pub-dates>
      </dates>
      <abstract>Transportation systems generate certain health-promoting benefits such as access to social, economic, and
cultural resources, but they also are a source of air pollution, noise, safety hazards, and barriers that
diminish social cohesion in neighborhoods. Streets, in particular, are among the most important forms of
public space in cities, yet they also are a main source of exposure to the negative externalities of traffic. It
is estimated that between 4 and 19 percent of the U.S. population lives close to high-traffic roads,
depending on assumptions about distance and types of roadway. These proportions are higher for
minority and low-income populations. Although the relationships between traffic exposure, race, and
socio-economic status have been consistent and reproducible, they have also been spatially heterogeneous
with limited investigation into the patterns or causes of the heterogeneity. Using spatially-explicit
statistical techniques, we examined variation in residential exposure to traffic at regional and
neighborhood levels with race and socio-economic status as variables of interest. We found that minority
and lower socio-economic status are systematically linked to higher exposure to traffic in Denver,
Colorado at both regional- and neighborhood-level scales.</abstract>
      <periodical><full-title>Mountain-Plains Consortium Region 8</full-title></periodical>
      <keywords>
      </keywords>
      <urls>
        <related-urls>
        </related-urls>
      </urls>
    </record>
    <record>
      <ref-type name="Journal Article"></ref-type>
      <contributors>
        <authors>
          <author>
            McAndrews, Carolyn
          </author>
        </authors>
        <secondary-authors>
        </secondary-authors>
      </contributors>
      <titles>
        <title>Transportation, Land Use, and Environmental Planning</title>
      </titles>
      <dates>
        <year>2020</year>
          <pub-dates>
            <date>11</date>
          </pub-dates>
      </dates>
      <pages>35-53</pages>
      <abstract>The relationship between transportation and public health has been a concern of policy and planning for decades, centering on air quality, safety, and physical activity. Despite improved understanding of transportation as an environmental determinant of health, we lack critical knowledge of how streets, traffic, and land use interact as social determinants of health. Streets are among the most important forms of public space in cities. As such, they display the material signs of social problems and neglect such as graffiti, drug and alcohol use, and squalor, which are known social pathways that affect health. This chapter provides a critical summary of how transportation and land use can be understood as a social pathway of health and health disparities. It illustrates this idea with the case of major arterial roads. Arterial roads are an explicit example of why social-ecological health impacts are increasingly a focus of transportation policy, particularly as cities and regions locate infill and transit-oriented development along high-traffic streets and highways.</abstract>
      <periodical><full-title>Elsevier</full-title></periodical>
      <keywords>
      </keywords>
      <urls>
        <related-urls>
          <url>https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.sciencedirect.com&#x2F;science&#x2F;article&#x2F;pii&#x2F;B9780128151679000037#</url>
        </related-urls>
      </urls>
    </record>
    <record>
      <ref-type name="Journal Article"></ref-type>
      <contributors>
        <authors>
          <author>
            Mirza, Noeman A.
          </author>
          <author>
            Hulko, Wendy
          </author>
        </authors>
        <secondary-authors>
        </secondary-authors>
      </contributors>
      <titles>
        <title>The complex nature of transportation as a key determinant of health in primary and community care restructuring initiatives in rural Canada</title>
      </titles>
      <dates>
        <year>2022</year>
          <pub-dates>
            <date>3</date>
          </pub-dates>
      </dates>
      <volume>60</volume>
      <pages>101002</pages>
      <electronic-resource-num>10.1016&#x2F;j.jaging.2022.101002</electronic-resource-num>
      <abstract>It is well recognized that transportation is a barrier to healthcare access for rural-dwelling residents, particularly older adults. Healthcare restructuring initiatives seldom take into consideration the complexity of transportation, which acts as a barrier to appropriate and timely access to healthcare services for older adults in rural communities. This article presents findings of a qualitative research study that explored the complex nature of transportation challenges that rural-dwelling older adults experience in Western Canada when trying to access primary and community care services. Data were derived from a larger study of service user views on a healthcare restructuring initiative intended to facilitate aging-in-place. We conducted 15 focus groups and 9 interviews with a diverse sample of 83 older adults living in one urban centre and nine rural and small rural towns in British Columbia (BC)’s interior. We used content analysis to determine codes and derive themes. Study findings showed that transportation was a top priority for improving primary and community care. Older adult participants identified a range of transportation challenges in trying to get to healthcare services and care providers getting to them. Transportation was a social determinant of health (SDOH) for all participants, regardless of whether they lived in the urban centre or in a rural or small rural town. Our study provides more evidence to support that transportation is a key SDOH for rural-dwelling older adults. As such, transportation should be specifically addressed in healthcare restructuring initiatives that aim to support aging-in-place. Service providers need to advocate for system-wide solutions such as integrating transportation into the healthcare system, while it is imperative that decision-makers act on these solutions.</abstract>
      <periodical><full-title>Journal of Aging Studies</full-title></periodical>
      <keywords>
      </keywords>
      <urls>
        <related-urls>
        </related-urls>
      </urls>
    </record>
    <record>
      <ref-type name="Journal Article"></ref-type>
      <contributors>
        <authors>
          <author>
            Neutens, Tijs
          </author>
        </authors>
        <secondary-authors>
        </secondary-authors>
      </contributors>
      <titles>
        <title>Accessibility, equity and health care: review and research directions for transport geographers</title>
      </titles>
      <dates>
        <year>2015</year>
          <pub-dates>
            <date>2</date>
          </pub-dates>
      </dates>
      <volume>43</volume>
      <pages>14-27</pages>
      <electronic-resource-num>10.1016&#x2F;j.jtrangeo.2014.12.006</electronic-resource-num>
      <abstract>Research at the confluence of accessibility, equity and health is flourishing. And yet, there is only slow and modest progress in terms of improving the spatial and temporal accuracy of measuring accessibility and equity of accessibility to health care services. This paper critically reviews the latest methodological and empirical research developments and trends in this area through a transport geography lens. More specifically, this paper discusses recent accomplishments in terms of modeling accessibility and provides a systematic and comprehensive literature review of their application in empirical studies of health care delivery. Based on this literature review a research agenda is put forward, identifying knowledge gaps that transport researchers can help to fill. These knowledge gaps pertain to the need for more spatially disaggregated, individualized and temporally-aware accessibility metrics, more sophisticated geocomputational tools to operationalize such metrics and improved measurement of equity considerations in empirical research.</abstract>
      <periodical><full-title>Journal of Transport Geography</full-title></periodical>
      <keywords>
      </keywords>
      <urls>
        <related-urls>
        </related-urls>
      </urls>
    </record>
    <record>
      <ref-type name="Journal Article"></ref-type>
      <contributors>
        <authors>
          <author>
            Peris, Eulalia
          </author>
          <author>
            Fenech, Benjamin
          </author>
        </authors>
        <secondary-authors>
        </secondary-authors>
      </contributors>
      <titles>
        <title>Associations and effect modification between transportation noise, self-reported response to noise and the wider determinants of health: A narrative synthesis of the literature</title>
      </titles>
      <dates>
        <year>2020</year>
          <pub-dates>
            <date>12</date>
          </pub-dates>
      </dates>
      <volume>748</volume>
      <pages>141040</pages>
      <electronic-resource-num>10.1016&#x2F;j.scitotenv.2020.141040</electronic-resource-num>
      <abstract>Noise and health guidance to date have focused on the direct links between noise and health outcomes such as annoyance, sleep disturbance, cardiovascular and metabolic disease, and cognitive impairment in schoolchildren. However, noise is a psychosocial stressor, and there are individual studies showing that exposure to noise or the self-reported responses to noise may affect health through interactions with the wider determinants of health and well-being including physical activity, use of green spaces and social interactions. Despite this emerging evidence concerning potential impacts of noise on the wider determinants of health, literature in the field remains dispersed and unsynthesised. This study seeks to synthetize evidence on different relationships between transportation noise, self-reported responses to noise and the wider determinants of health using a systematic review methodology. The search was conducted in Medline, PsycINFO, PubMed, and Scopus on articles published from 2000 to 2017. This led to the review of 76 papers which satisfied the inclusion criteria. Despite strong heterogeneity in the studies&#39; methodologies and indicators used, there is some evidence that noise exposure and responses to noise such as annoyance and disturbance are associated with people&#39;s lifestyle, recreational activities as well as the local economy of the neighbourhood. On the other hand, there are some wider determinants of health, mainly those related to the built and natural environment, which modify the relationship between noise exposure and self-reported responses to noise. In particular, greenness, having access to quiet areas, and covering noise sources either visually or acoustically with natural features seems to decrease people&#39;s negative responses to noise. Results indicate that transportation noise has the potential to affect health through various pathways, and a holistic approach is needed to capture all the effects.</abstract>
      <periodical><full-title>Science of The Total Environment</full-title></periodical>
      <keywords>
      </keywords>
      <urls>
        <related-urls>
        </related-urls>
      </urls>
    </record>
    <record>
      <ref-type name="Journal Article"></ref-type>
      <contributors>
        <authors>
          <author>
            Solomon, Eli M.
          </author>
          <author>
            Wing, Holly
          </author>
          <author>
            Steiner, John F.
          </author>
          <author>
            Gottlieb, Laura M.
          </author>
        </authors>
        <secondary-authors>
        </secondary-authors>
      </contributors>
      <titles>
        <title>Impact of Transportation Interventions on Health Care Outcomes</title>
      </titles>
      <dates>
        <year>2020</year>
          <pub-dates>
            <date>4</date>
          </pub-dates>
      </dates>
      <volume>58</volume>
      <pages>384-391</pages>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <electronic-resource-num>10.1097&#x2F;MLR.0000000000001292</electronic-resource-num>
      <abstract>Introduction: 
Lack of reliable transportation can be a barrier to keeping appointments or accessing other health care services. Increasingly, insurers and health care delivery systems subsidize transportation services for patients. This systematic review synthesizes existing research on nonemergency medical transportation interventions.
Methods: 
We searched 3 databases (Embase, PubMed, Google) for studies of health care sector-sponsored programs that provided patients assistance with nonemergency transportation and directly assessed the impact of transportation assistance on health and health care utilization outcomes. Studies meeting inclusion criteria were graded for quality using standard grading criteria.
Findings: 
Eight studies met all inclusion criteria. Most were rated as low quality. All studies included examined process or health care utilization outcomes, such as uptake of transportation services, return for follow-up, or missed appointment rates; only 1 included health outcomes, such as illness severity and blood pressure. Results were mixed. More rigorous studies showed low patient uptake of transportation services and inconsistent impacts on health and utilization outcomes.
Conclusions: 
Despite considerable interest in subsidizing transportation services to improve health for patients facing transportation barriers, little rigorously conducted research has demonstrated the impact of transportation services on health or health care utilization. Some extant literature suggests that transportation assistance is more likely to be effective when offered with other interventions to reduce social and economic barriers to health.</abstract>
      <periodical><full-title>Medical Care</full-title></periodical>
      <keywords>
      </keywords>
      <urls>
        <related-urls>
        </related-urls>
      </urls>
    </record>
    <record>
      <ref-type name="Journal Article"></ref-type>
      <contributors>
        <authors>
          <author>
            Towne, Samuel D.
          </author>
          <author>
            Liu, Xiaojun
          </author>
          <author>
            Li, Rui
          </author>
          <author>
            Smith, Matthew Lee
          </author>
          <author>
            Maddock, Jay E.
          </author>
          <author>
            Tan, Anran
          </author>
          <author>
            Hayek, Samah
          </author>
          <author>
            Zelber-Sagi, Shira
          </author>
          <author>
            Jiang, Xiaoqing
          </author>
          <author>
            Ruan, Haotian
          </author>
          <author>
            Yuan, Zhaokang
          </author>
        </authors>
        <secondary-authors>
        </secondary-authors>
      </contributors>
      <titles>
        <title>Social and Structural Determinants of Health Inequities: Socioeconomic, Transportation-Related, and Provincial-Level Indicators of Cost-Related Forgone Hospital Care in China</title>
      </titles>
      <dates>
        <year>2021</year>
          <pub-dates>
            <date>6</date>
          </pub-dates>
      </dates>
      <volume>18</volume>
      <pages>6113</pages>
      <issue>11</issue>
      <electronic-resource-num>10.3390&#x2F;ijerph18116113</electronic-resource-num>
      <abstract>Despite near universal health insurance coverage in China, populations with low incomes may still face barriers in access and utilization of affordable health care. We aimed to identify the likelihood of forgone medical care due to cost by surveying individuals from the community to assess: (1) The percent with forgone medical care due to cost; and (2) Factors associated with forgone medical care due to cost. Surveys conducted (2016–2017) in Mandarin included demographic and medical care utilization-related items. Theoretically-informed, fully-adjusted analyses were employed. Approximately 94% of respondents had health insurance, which is somewhat similar to national estimates. Overall, 24% of respondents resided in rural areas, with 18% having less than a high school education, and 49% being male. More than 36% reported forgone medical care due to cost in the past 12 months. In fully-adjusted analyses, having lower education, generally not being satisfied with the commute to the hospital, and being a resident of a province with a lower density of physicians were associated with forgone medical care. Cost-related disparities in the access and utilization of needed medical care persist, even with near universal health insurance, which may be due to one’s satisfaction with travel time to healthcare and other community assets.</abstract>
      <periodical><full-title>International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health</full-title></periodical>
      <keywords>
      </keywords>
      <urls>
        <related-urls>
        </related-urls>
      </urls>
    </record>
    <record>
      <ref-type name="Journal Article"></ref-type>
      <contributors>
        <authors>
          <author>
            Zettler, Marjorie E
          </author>
          <author>
            Feinberg, Bruce A
          </author>
          <author>
            Jeune-Smith, Yolaine
          </author>
          <author>
            Gajra, Ajeet
          </author>
        </authors>
        <secondary-authors>
        </secondary-authors>
      </contributors>
      <titles>
        <title>Impact of social determinants of health on cancer care: a survey of community oncologists</title>
      </titles>
      <dates>
        <year>2021</year>
          <pub-dates>
            <date>10</date>
          </pub-dates>
      </dates>
      <volume>11</volume>
      <pages>e049259</pages>
      <issue>10</issue>
      <electronic-resource-num>10.1136&#x2F;bmjopen-2021-049259</electronic-resource-num>
      <abstract>Objective Cancer survival rates have improved over the past few decades, yet socioeconomic disparities persist. Social determinants of health (SDOH) have consistently been shown to correlate with health outcomes. The objective of this study was to characterise oncologists’ perceptions of the impact of SDOH on their patients, and their opinions on how these effects could be remediated.
Design Cross-sectional survey of physicians.
Setting Web-based survey completed prior to live meetings held between February and April 2020.
Participants Oncologists&#x2F;haematologists from across the USA.
Exposure Clinical practice in a community-based or hospital-based setting.
Main outcome and measure Physician responses regarding how SDOH affected their patients, which factors represented the most significant barriers to optimal health outcomes and how the impact of SDOH could be mitigated through assistance programmes.
Results Of the 165 physicians who completed the survey, 93% agreed that SDOH had a significant impact on their patients’ health outcomes. Financial security&#x2F;lack of insurance and access to transportation were identified most often as the greatest barriers for their patients (83% and 58%, respectively). Eighty-one per cent of physicians indicated that they and their staff had limited time to spend assisting patients with social needs, and 76% reported that assistance programmes were not readily accessible. Government organisations, hospitals, non-profit organisations and commercial payers were selected by 50% or more of oncologists surveyed as who should be responsible for delivering assistance programmes to patients with social needs; 42% indicated that pharmaceutical manufacturers should also be responsible.
Conclusion Our survey found that most oncologists were aware of the impact of SDOH on their patients but were constrained in their time to assist patients with social needs. The physicians in our study identified a need for more accessible assistance programmes and greater involvement from all stakeholders in addressing SDOH to improve health outcomes.</abstract>
      <periodical><full-title>BMJ Open</full-title></periodical>
      <keywords>
      </keywords>
      <urls>
        <related-urls>
        </related-urls>
      </urls>
    </record>
  </records>
</xml>